Finding Aid for the Nikki Colodny papers LSC.2188
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nikki Colodny papers
1978-1995
UCLA Library Special Collections
Colodny, Nikki
LSC.2188
1.6 linear feet (4 boxes)
Dr. Nikki Colodny was a pro-choice activist, abortion provider, and women's health advocate operating in Toronto, Ontario throughout the 1980s and 1990s. This collection contains records from several clinics and advocacy organizations with which she was active, in addition to press coverage of her activities and research materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 2013. Donated by Nikki Colodny.
This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973770763606533
Sponsor
The June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA is an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library. These collections expand the pool of primary source materials available to researchers and to the community at large. This partnership was initiated by CSW and is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) to inventory, organize, preserve, and digitize more than eighty Mazer collections pertaining to lesbian and feminist activism and writings.
Biography
Dr. Nikki Colodny (born April 1, 1948), was a Canadian abortion provider, women's health advocate and activist operating in Toronto, Ontario throughout the 1980s and 1990s. Most prominently, she worked with Dr. Henry Morgentaler, providing medical care and abortion services which at the time were illegal. Their arrests and repeated harassment brought publicity to their cause, eventually precipitating the overturn of abortion laws by the Supreme Court of Canada in 1988. In that same year, Colodny founded the cooperative Women's Choice Health Clinic. In addition to her medical services, she was an active participant in several pro-choice organizations including the Ontario Coalition of Abortion Clinics (OCAC), the National Abortion Federation (NAF), and the Canadian Abortion Rights Action League (CARAL). Her research is widely published in both medical and women's studies academic journals.
Scope and Content
This collection contains organizational records from the Choice in Health Clinic as well as from several operational Canadian pro-choice activist organizations. Also included is press coverage of abortion rights in Canada as well as more specific coverage of Dr. Nikki Colodny and Dr. Henry Morgentaler's legal battles. A small amount of photographs and personal correspondence are represented in the collection, but the majority of materials deal with Dr. Colodny's professional activities.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials in this collection are arranged chronologically.
June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA.; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives.; Morgentaler, Henry -- Archives; Colodny, Nikki -- Archives
- Official reports: Court and legal proceedings, 1977-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Canadian Medical Association, 1978-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Canadian Dimension, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Content
  Volume 15, Number 1 & 2 (October/November 1980); Labour Supplement (1983); Volume 18, Number 5 (June 1984); Volume 18, Number 6 (December 1984/January 1985)
- Notes and personal items, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ephemera: stickers, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Medical Licensing, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Agenda: That Which Must Be Done, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Vol. 1 No. 6 (January 1982); Vol. 1 No. 7 (March 1982); Vol. 2 No. 1/2 (Sept/Oct 1982); Vol. 2 No. 3 Special Issue (June 1983)
- Pamphlets, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Medical Reform Group, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- National Action Committee on the Status of Women, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Fact sheets and briefs, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The National Democratic Party (NDP), 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Published Research Material: medical, legal, feminist, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Doctors for Choice, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Anti-choice materials, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Dr. Morgentaler and Dr. Colodny arrests, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Fliers, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Fliers for rallies, events, and gatherings predominantly around abortion rights and the pro-choice movement.
- Programs and conference materials, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Ontario Coalition for Abortion Clinics (OCAC), 1985-1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- National Abortion Federation (NAF), 1985-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Court case (Pro-Choice Defence Fund), 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Concerned Citizens for Choice on Abortion (CCCA)- Vancouver, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Press releases and letters, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1986-1998 (Box 3, Folder 1, Box 2, Folder 11)
- Coalition for Access to Abortion, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Report on Therapeutic Abortion Services in Ontario, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Canadian Abortion Rights Action League, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Campaign Life Coalition News (December 1987, March 1988), YWCA Access (1987 Summer), Concerned Citizens for Choice on Abortion (October 1987)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Supporting organizations funding letters, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Press releases, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Independent Health Facilities Act, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Financial statements and proposals, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Choice in Health Clinic: External correspondence, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Training and hiring, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Clinique Planning Familial & Sexualite, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Contains blank patient forms and general information about abortion.
- Birth control in service materials, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Internal correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Trademarks, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- IPAS Gynecologic Aspiration Kit with Karman Cannulae and Syringes, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Training materials, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Ministry of Health Task Group, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Doctor training, 1992-1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Choice in Health Clinic: Harassment suit Affidavits: Ontario Court (General Division), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Protests and harassment outside of abortion clinics, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Homophobia, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Gordon Watson case, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Methotrexate and Misoprostol induced abortion, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)